Guide to the Lenora Champagne Papers 1984-1991 MSS 153
© 2010 Fales Library and Special Collections
Lenora Champagne Papers
1984 - 1991
MSS 153
© 2010 Fales Library and Special Collections
5.0 linear feet
Champagne, Lenora
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers. Appointments are necessary for the use of manuscript and archival collections.
Scope and Content note
This collection is comprised of video footage of numerous performances by Lenora Champagne between 1984-1991.
Biographical Note
Lenora Champagne (www.lenorachampagne.com) came to New York from Louisiana to be a painter, but found her voice in performance. Since receiving her Ph.D. in Performance Studies from NYU in 1980, Champagne has been making work as a performance artist, playwright, and director. She received a NYFA Fellowship in Playwriting in 1998 and a NYFA Fellowship in Performance Art in 2003. Champagne has been awarded three fellowships from the National Endowment for the Arts (in solo performance, directing, and an artist's residency in Canada); recieved commissions and project support from NYSCA, DCA, the Peg Santvoord Foundation, the Joyce Gilmore Foundation, the Jerome Foundation, the Puffin Foundation, the Franklin Furnace Fund for Performance Art, among others; and has been in residence at the MacDowell Colony and Yaddo. Her work in galleries and arts spaces such as Franklin Furnace, the New Museum, and Creative Time's Art on the Beach is mostly live performance, though she also co-created an installation for the New Museum's Art Mall as Social Space show in 1992, and wrapped babies in words for Shattered Anatomies, a box anthology of objects and texts on performance, Arnolfini, 1997. Champagne frequently collaborates with sculptors, installation artists, and media artists. She is an alumna of New Dramatists, a former resident HARP artist at HERE Arts Center (where she developed TRACES/fades, an intergenerational performance with music and video that is a meditation on memory, loss, and our national inability to remember history), and is Professor of Theatre and Performance at Purchase College, SUNY. Champagne edited and contributed to Out From Under: Texts by Women Performance Artists (Theatre Communications Group, 1990); her publications include performance texts, plays and essays published by Smith & Kraus, Performing Arts Journal, Performance Research, Plays and Playwrights 2009 and The Iowa Review.
Arrangement
The materials in this collection are arranged alphabetically.
- Series I: Video
  Conditions Governing Access
  Researchers may request to view material from Subseries B: Access Copies.
  - Subseries A: Originals
    - As Ready, Apart From Herself - Pick Up Shots (at Franklin Furnace), 1986 (Box 1, Media ID: 153.0013)
      Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
      Format: 3/4" U-Matic
      TRT: [00:10:00]
    - As Ready, Apart From Herself, Written & Directed by Lenora Champagne, Recorded 16 May 1986 (Box 1, Media ID: 153.0012)
      TRT: [00:34:00]
    - Eye of the Garden Complete, Undated (Box 2, Media ID: 153.0023)
      TRT: [00:48:00]
    - Eye of the Garden - Tape 1 of 3, Undated (Box 2, Media ID: 153.0022)
      TRT: [00:15:00]
    - Eye of the Garden - Tape 2 of 3, Undated (Box 2, Media ID: 153.0020)
      TRT: [00:21:00]
    - Eye of the Garden - Tape 3 of 3, Undated (Box 2, Media ID: 153.0021)
      TRT: [00:17:00]
    - Fractured Juliet by Lenora Champagne (at Real Art Ways), 1985 - 1986 (Box 1, Media ID: 153.0010)
      TRT: [00:23:00]
    - Fractured Juliet, Getting Over Tom (studio version taped at Real Art Ways), circa 1986 (Box 1, Media ID: 153.0007)
      TRT: [00:13:00]
    - Home: A Performance by Lenora Champagne (at Danspace Project), 1986 (Box 1, Media ID: 153.0015)
      TRT: [00:45:00]
    - Isabella Dreams The New World Reel #1, 1990 (Box 1, Media ID: 153.0005)
      TRT: [01:01:00]
    - Isabella Dreams The New World Reel #2, 1990 (Box 1, Media ID: 153.0006)
      TRT: [00:26:00]
    - Lenora Champagne: "Fractured Juliet," "The Eye of the Garden" (Excerpts), Undated (Box 1, Media ID: 153.0008)
      TRT: [00:37:00]
    - Lenora Champagne, Reptile Warmth (excerpt with video treatment), 1985 (Box 1, Media ID: 153.0001)
    - Lenora Champagne with Kevin Duffy and Patricia Pretzinger P.S. 122, 19 November 1984 [1] - From The Red Light District (Box 1, Media ID: 153.0014)
      TRT: [00:51:00]
    - "Lenora's Tape" (taped at Real Art Ways): [1] - Getting Over Tom [2] - Fractured Juliet [3] - The Ways to the River [4] - Reptile Warmth (excerpt), circa 1986 (Box 1, Media ID: 153.0009)
      TRT: [00:54:00]
    - [1] - Manna [2] - Flying Home, Undated (Box 2, Media ID: 153.0024)
      TRT: [00:46:00]
    - Manna, Unedited Original - Tape 1, Undated (Box 2, Media ID: 153.0017)
      TRT: [00:22:00]
    - Manna - Tape 2, Undated (Box 2, Media ID: 153.0018)
      TRT: [00:20:00]
    - Manna - Tape 3, Undated (Box 2, Media ID: 153.0019)
    - Master: Excerpts from Works by Lenora Champagne, [1] - As Ready, Apart from Herself [2] - Home [3] - Eye of the Gardent [4] - Fractured Juliet [5] - From the Red Light District [6] - Manna [7] - Getting Over Tom [8] - Fractured Juliet, Undated (Box 1, Media ID: 153.0003)
      TRT: [00:24:00]
    - Monsters, "The Face" (Performance in Support of the NEA, Master Tape from MK's), 1990 - 1991 (Box 1, Media ID: 153.0004)
      TRT: [00:28:45]
    - Reptile Warmth, April 18, 85, Nicky Keiji, 2nd Take Copy, 1985 (Box 1, Media ID: 153.0002)
      TRT: [00:11:00]
    - Winter Heat: A Performance by Lenora Champagne with Andre Gribou, Recorded 18 January 1987 (Box 1, Media ID: 153.0011)
      TRT: [00:50:00]
    - Women Without Parts - Written & Performed by Lenora Champagne, Recorded 11 January 1988 (Box 2, Media ID: 153.0016)
      TRT: [00:40:00]
  - Subseries B: Access Copies
    - As Ready, Apart From Herself - Pick Up Shots (at Franklin Furnace), 1986 (Shelf Media, Media ID: 153.0063)
      Format: DVD
      Original Format: 3/4" U-Matic
    - As Ready, Apart From Herself, Written & Directed by Lenora Champagne, Recorded 16 May 1986 (Shelf Media, Media ID: 153.0060)
    - Eye of the Garden Complete, Undated (Shelf Media, Media ID: 153.0093)
    - Eye of the Garden - Tape 1 of 3, Undated (Shelf Media, Media ID: 153.0090)
    - Eye of the Garden - Tape 2 of 3, Undated (Shelf Media, Media ID: 153.0084)
    - Eye of the Garden - Tape 3 of 3, Undated (Shelf Media, Media ID: 153.0087)
    - Fractured Juliet by Lenora Champagne (at Real Art Ways), 1985 - 1986 (Shelf Media, Media ID: 153.0054)
    - Fractured Juliet, Getting Over Tom (studio version taped at Real Art Ways), circa 1986 (Shelf Media, Media ID: 153.0045)
    - Home: A Performance by Lenora Champagne (at Danspace Project), 1986 (Shelf Media, Media ID: 153.0069)
    - Isabella Dreams The New World Reel #1, 1990 (Shelf Media, Media ID: 153.0039)
      Original Format: 3/4" U-matic
    - Isabella Dreams The New World Reel #2, 1990 (Shelf Media, Media ID: 153.0042)
    - Lenora Champagne: "Fractured Juliet," "The Eye of the Garden" (Excerpts), Undated (Shelf Media, Media ID: 153.0048)
      TRT: [00:39:00]
    - Lenora Champagne, "Reptile Warmth" (excerpt, with video treatment), 1985 (Shelf Media, Media ID: 153.0027)
    - Lenora Champagne with Kevin Duffy and Patricia Pretzinger P.S. 122, 19 November 1984 [1] - From the Red Light District (Shelf Media, Media ID: 153.0066)
    - "Lenora's Tape" (taped at Real Art Ways): [1] - Getting Over Tom [2] - Fractured Juliet [3] - The Ways to the River [4] - Reptile Warmth (excerpt), circa 1986 (Shelf Media, Media ID: 153.0051)
    - [1] - Manna [2] - Flying Home, Undated (Shelf Media, Media ID: 153.0096)
    - Manna, Unedited Original - Tape 1, Undated (Shelf Media, Media ID: 153.0075)
    - Manna - Tape 2, Undated (Shelf Media, Media ID: 153.0078)
    - Manna - Tape 3, Undated (Shelf Media, Media ID: 153.0081)
    - Master: Excerpts from Works by Lenora Champagne, [1] - As Ready, Apart from Herself [2] - Home [3] - Eye of the Gardent [4] - Fractured Juliet [5] - From the Red Light District [6] - Manna [7] - Getting Over Tom [8] - Fractured Juliet, Undated (Shelf Media, Media ID: 153.0033)
    - Monsters, "The Face" (Performance in Support of the NEA, Master Tape from MK's), 1990 - 1991 (Shelf Media, Media ID: 153.0036)
      TRT: [00:32:00]
    - Reptile Warmth, April 18, 85, Nicky Keiji, 2nd Take Copy, 1985 (Shelf Media, Media ID: 153.0030)
    - Winter Heat: A Performance by Lenora Champagne with Andre Gribou, Recorded 18 January 1987 (Shelf Media, Media ID: 153.0057)
    - Women Without Parts, Written & Performed by Lenora Champagne, Recorded 11 January 1988 (Shelf Media, Media ID: 153.0072)